I grew up in Europe, and World War II caught me
لقد نشأت في أوروبا، وعانيت من الحرب العالمية الثانية
when I was between seven and 10 years old.
بين السنتين السابعة والعاشرة من عمري
And I realized how few of the grown-ups that I knew
وأدركت كم كان قليلا عدد الراشدين ممن كنت أعرفهم
were able to withstand the tragedies that the war visited on them --
الذين استطاعوا تحمل المآسي التي أصابتهم جراء الحرب
how few of them could even resemble a normal, contented,
وكم أن قليلا منهم قد استطاع حتى محاكاة حياة عادية مطمئنة
satisfied, happy life once their job, their home, their security
وراضية وسعيدة عندما لحق الدمار وظائفهم وبيوتهم وأمنهم
was destroyed by the war.
بسبب الحرب
So I became interested in understanding
ولذلك أصبحت مهتمًا بفهم الأمور
what contributed to a life that was worth living.
التي تساهم في خلق حياة جديرة بأن نعيشها.
And I tried, as a child, as a teenager, to read philosophy
وحاولت في طفولتي ومراهقتي أن أقرأ في الفلسفة
and to get involved in art and religion and many other ways
وأن أدخل إلى عالم الفن والدين، وحاولت كثيرًا من الطرق الأخرى
that I could see as a possible answer to that question.
التي كنت أرى أنها قد تحمل إجابة على هذا السؤال.
And finally I ended up encountering psychology by chance.
وانتهى بي الأمر أخيرًا إلى أن وجدت علم النفس بالصدفة.
I was at a ski resort in Switzerland without any money
كنت في الواقع في منتجع للتزلج في سويسرا، دون أي مال
to actually enjoy myself, because the snow had melted and
يسمح لي بالاستمتاع، لأن الثلج كان قد ذاب وكان هناك --
I didn't have money to go to a movie. But I found that on the --
لم يكن معي مال لأذهب إلى السينما، ولكني وجدت على --
I read in the newspapers that there was to be a presentation
قرأت في الصحف أنه ستكون هناك محاضرة
by someone in a place that I'd seen in the center of Zurich,
يلقيها شخص ما في مكان كنت قد رأيته في وسط زيوريخ
and it was about flying saucers [that] he was going to talk.
وكان سيتكلم عن الأطباق الطائرة.
And I thought, well, since I can't go to the movies,
فقلت لنفسي، بما أني لا أستطيع الذهاب إلى السينما
at least I will go for free to listen to flying saucers.
بإمكاني على الأقل أن أذهب مجانًا للاستماع إلى الأطباق الطائرة
And the man who talked at that evening lecture was very interesting.
وكان الرجل الذي تكلم في تلك المحاضرة المسائية مشوقًا للغاية
Instead of talking about little green men,
وقد -- في الواقع بدلا من أن يتحدث عن أقزام خضر
he talked about how the psyche of the Europeans
فقد تحدث عن نفسية الأوروبيين
had been traumatized by the war, and now they're projecting
وكيف سببت لها الحرب صدمة، وأنهم الآن يبعثون
flying saucers into the sky.
الأطباق الطائرة إلى السماء، كما كان --
He talked about how the mandalas of ancient Hindu religion
تكلم عن أن دوائر الماندالا الخاصة بالديانة الهندوسية في العصور القديمة
were kind of projected into the sky as an attempt to regain
كانت تقذف إلى السماء في محاولة لاسترجاع
some sense of order after the chaos of war.
شيء من النظام بعد فوضى الحرب
And this seemed very interesting to me.
وبدا ذلك لي شيقًا للغاية
And I started reading his books after that lecture.
وبدأت أقرا كتبه بعد تلك المحاضرة
And that was Carl Jung, whose name or work I had no idea about.
وكان ذلك الرجل كارل يونج، الذي لم يكن لدي أدنى فكرة عن اسمه أو عمله
Then I came to this country to study psychology
ثم أتيت إلى هذا البلد لأدرس علم النفس
and I started trying to understand the roots of happiness.
وبدأت في محاولة فهم جذور السعادة هذه
This is a typical result that many people have presented,
وهذه نتيجة طبيعية ظهرت عند كثير من الناس
and there are many variations on it.
وهناك عدة أشكال مختلفة لها
But this, for instance, shows that about 30 percent of the people
ولكن هذا، مثلا، يبين أن نحو 30 في المئة
surveyed in the United States since 1956
من المستطلعين في الولايات المتحدة منذ 1956
say that their life is very happy.
يقولون إن حياتهم سعيدة جدًا
And that hasn't changed at all.
ولم يتغير ذلك مطلقا
Whereas the personal income,
وقد زاد الدخل الشخصي
on a scale that has been held constant to accommodate for inflation,
بمستوى أبقي ثابتًا لاستيعاب التضخم
has more than doubled, almost tripled, in that period.
بأكثر من الضعف بل كادت الزيادة تصل إلى ثلاثة أضعاف خلال تلك الفترة
But you find essentially the same results,
ولكننا نجد نفس النتائج تقريبًا
namely, that after a certain basic point -- which corresponds more or less
وهي أن بعد نقطة أساسية بعينها تعادل تقريبًا
to just a few 1,000 dollars above the minimum poverty level --
ما يزيد عن المستوى الأدنى للفقر ببضعة آلاف قليلة من الدولارات
increases in material well-being don't seem to affect how happy people are.
لا يبدو أن الزيادات في الرفاهية المادية تؤثر على مدى سعادة الناس
In fact, you can find that the lack of basic resources,
وفي الواقع، بإمكاننا أن نجد أن النقص في الموارد الأساسية
material resources, contributes to unhappiness,
والموارد المادية يساهم في انعدام السعادة
but the increase in material resources does not increase happiness.
ولكن الزيادة في الموارد المالية لا تزيد السعادة
So my research has been focused more on --
ولذلك ركز بحثي بشكل أكبر على --
after finding out these things that actually corresponded
بعد أن توصلت لهذه الأمور التي تتطابق في الواقع
to my own experience, I tried to understand:
مع تجربتي الشخصية، حاولت حينئذ أن أفهم
where -- in everyday life, in our normal experience --
في أي جزء من حياتنا اليومية، في الأحداث العادية التي تحدث لنا
do we feel really happy?
نشعر بالسعادة حقًا
And to start
ولكي أبدأ في ذلك --
those studies about 40 years ago, I began to look at creative people --
هذه الدراسات من أربعين سنة، بدأت في النظر إلى المبدعين --
first artists and scientists, and so forth -- trying to understand
الفنانين والعلماء أولا وهلم جرا -- في محاولة لفهم الأمر
what made them feel that it was worth essentially spending their life
الذي جعلهم يشعرون بأنه يستحق منهم أن يقضوا حياتهم
doing things for which many of them didn't expect either fame or fortune,
في العمل لأجله - كثير منهم لم ينتظر لا الشهرة ولا الثروة -
but which made their life meaningful and worth doing.
ذلك الأمر الذي جعل حياتهم ذات معنى وجعل عيشها ذا قيمة
This was one of the leading composers of American music back in the '70s.
كان هذا أحد الملحنين الرائدين في الموسيقى الأمريكية في السبيعينيات
And the interview was 40 pages long.
سجلت المقابلة في أربعين صفحة
But this little excerpt is a very good summary
ولكن هذا الاقتباس الصغير يلخص بشكل ممتاز
of what he was saying during the interview.
ما كان يقوله أثناء المقابلة
And it describes how he feels when composing is going well.
كما يصف كيف كان الملحن يشعر عندما كان يسير التلحين بشكل جيد
And he says by describing it as an ecstatic state.
ويصف الأمر بأنه حالة من الاستغراق (ecstasy)
Now, "ecstasy" in Greek meant
تعني كلمة (ecstasy) في اللغة اليونانية القديمة
simply to stand to the side of something.
الوقوف بجانب شيء ما
And then it became essentially an analogy for a mental state
ثم أصبح يضرب بها المثل لحالة عقلية
where you feel that you are not doing your ordinary everyday routines.
يشعر فيها المرء بأنه لا يقوم بالروتين اليومي لحياته العادية
So ecstasy is essentially a stepping into an alternative reality.
فالاستغراق إذًا هو دخول في واقع بديل
And it's interesting, if you think about it, how, when we think about
ومما يثير الاهتمام، إن تأملتم الأمر، أننا حين نفكر
the civilizations that we look up to as having been pinnacles of human achievement --
في الحضارات التي نعتبرها قد وصلت إلى قمة الإنجاز الإنساني --
whether it's China, Greece, the Hindu civilization,
سواء كانت الحضارة الصينية أو اليونانية أو الهندوسية
or the Mayas, or Egyptians -- what we know about them
أو حضارة المايا أو الحضارة المصرية -- نجد أن ما نعرفه عن هذه الحضارات
is really about their ecstasies, not about their everyday life.
هو في الحقيقة عن مظاهر الاستغراق عندهم، لا عن حياتهم اليومية
We know the temples they built, where people could come
نعرف المعابد التي بنوها حيث يذهب الناس
to experience a different reality.
ليشعروا بواقع مختلف
We know about the circuses,
نعرف ما كان عندهم من دور السيرك
the arenas, the theaters.
والحلبات والمسارح
These are the remains of civilizations and they are the places that people went
هذه هي أطلال الحضارات، وهي الأماكن التي ذهب الناس إليها
to experience life in a more concentrated, more ordered form.
ليجربوا الشعور بالحياة بشكل أكثر تركيزًا وأكثر نظاما
Now, this man doesn't need to go to a place like this,
لا يحتاج هذا الرجل إلى الذهاب إلى مكان مثل هذا
which is also -- this place, this arena, which is built
وهو كذلك -- هذا المكان، هذه الحلبة، الذي بني
like a Greek amphitheatre, is a place for ecstasy also.
على غرار استاد إغريقي، هو كذلك مكان للاستغراق
We are participating in a reality that is different
إننا نشارك في واقع مختلف
from that of the everyday life that we're used to.
عن حياتنا اليومية التي اعتدنا عليها
But this man doesn't need to go there.
ولكن هذا الرجل لا يحتاج لأن يذهب إلى هناك
He needs just a piece of paper where he can put down little marks,
كل ما يحتاجه هو ورقة يستطيع أن يكتب عليها بعض العلامات
and as he does that, he can imagine sounds
وبينما يفعل ذلك، بإمكانه تخيل الأصوات
that had not existed before in that particular combination.
التي لم تكن موجودة من قبل في هذا الترتيب
So once he gets to that point of beginning to create,
إذًا فحالما يصل إلى النقطة التي يبدأ منها في خلق --
like Jennifer did in her improvisation,
كما فعلت جنيفر في ارتجالها --
a new reality -- that is, a moment of ecstasy --
واقع جديد، فهذه لحظة استغراق
he enters that different reality.
وهو يدخل هذا الواقع المختلف
Now he says also that this is so intense an experience
يقول كذلك إن هذه التجربة شديدة للغاية
that it feels almost as if he didn't exist.
لدرجة أنه يشعر تقريبًا كما لو كان عدما
And that sounds like a kind of a romantic exaggeration.
ويبدو ذلك ضربًا من المبالغة الرومانسية
But actually, our nervous system is incapable of processing
ولكن جهازنا العصبي في الواقع غير قادر على معالجة
more than about 110 bits of information per second.
أكثر من 110 بِت من المعلومات في الثانية
And in order to hear me and understand what I'm saying,
ولكي تسمعني وتفهم ما أقوله
you need to process about 60 bits per second.
تحتاج لمعالجة 60 بِت في الثانية
That's why you can't hear more than two people.
ولذلك لا يستطيع الإنسان أن يسمع أكثر من شخصين
You can't understand more than two people talking to you.
ولا يستطيع الإنسان أن يفهم سوى شخصين ممن يتحدثون إليه
Well, when you are really involved in this completely engaging process
عندما تكون منهمكًا بقدر كبير في عملية تستغرقك تمامًا
of creating something new, as this man is,
مثل عملية إبتداع شيء جديد، مثلما يفعل هذا الرجل
he doesn't have enough attention left over to monitor
فلا يكون لديه ما يكفي من الانتباه لمراقبة
how his body feels, or his problems at home.
كيف يشعر جسمه، أو التفكير في مشاكله في المنزل
He can't feel even that he's hungry or tired.
لا يستطيع الشعور حتى بأنه جائع أو متعب
His body disappears,
يختفي جسمه
his identity disappears from his consciousness,
تختفي هويته من وعيه
because he doesn't have enough attention, like none of us do,
لأنه ليس لديه ما يكفي من الانتباه، بخلافنا جميعًا
to really do well something that requires a lot of concentration,
لأن يحسن أداء أمر يتطلب كثيرًا من التركيز
and at the same time to feel that he exists.
وأن يشعر في نفس الوقت بأنه موجود
So existence is temporarily suspended.
فالوجود إذًا يعلق مؤقتا
And he says that his hand seems to be moving by itself.
ويقول إن يده يبدو كأنها تتحرك من تلقاء نفسها
Now, I could look at my hand for two weeks, and I wouldn't feel
أما أنا فأستطيع أن أنظر إلى يدي لأسبوعين ولن أشعر
any awe or wonder, because I can't compose. (Laughter)
بأي رهبة أو دهشة، لأني لا أستطيع التلحين
So what it's telling you here
فإذًا ما نفهمه من هذا
is that obviously this automatic,
ولكن من أجزاء أخرى من المقابلة، أن هذه العملية التلقائية العفوية
spontaneous process that he's describing can only happen to someone
التي يصفها تحدث فقط لشخص
who is very well trained and who has developed technique.
مدرب بشكل جيد جدًا ونمى هذا الأسلوب
And it has become a kind of a truism in the study of creativity
ومما أصبح نوعًا من المسلمات في دراسة الإبداع
that you can't be creating anything with less than 10 years
أنك لا تستطيع إبتداع أي شيء قبل 10 سنوات
of technical-knowledge immersion in a particular field.
من الانغماس في المعرفة الفنية في مجال معين
Whether it's mathematics or music, it takes that long
سواء كان الرياضيات أو الموسيقى. هذه المدة
to be able to begin to change something in a way that it's better
ما تحتاجه لتبدأ في تغيير شيء بحيث يصير أفضل
than what was there before.
مما كان عليه قبل ذلك
Now, when that happens,
وعندما يحدث ذلك
he says the music just flows out.
يقول إن الموسيقي تخرج متدفقة
And because all of these people I started interviewing --
ولأن جميع الأشخاص الذين بدأت في إجراء مقابلات معهم --
this was an interview which is over 30 years old --
كانت هذه المقابلة من أكثر من ثلاثين سنة --
so many of the people described this as a spontaneous flow
كثير من الأشخاص وصف هذه الظاهرة بأنها تدفق عفوي
that I called this type of experience the "flow experience."
فأسميت هذا النوع من الشعور باسم "شعور التدفق".
And it happens in different realms.
وهو يحدث في مجالات مختلفة
For instance, a poet describes it in this form.
فمثلا، يصفه شاعر بهذا الشكل
This is by a student of mine who interviewed
هذا وصف من أحد طلابي قد أجرى مقابلات
some of the leading writers and poets in the United States.
مع بعض الكتاب والشعراء الرائدين في الولايات المتحدة
And it describes the same effortless, spontaneous feeling
ويصف نفس الإحساس غير المجهد والعفوي
that you get when you enter into this ecstatic state.
الذي تشعر به عندما تدخل في حالة الاستغراق هذه
This poet describes it as opening a door that floats in the sky --
يصف هذا الشاعر الأمر بأنه يشبه فتح باب يحلق في السماء
a very similar description to what Albert Einstein gave
أشبه كثيرًا بوصف ألبرت أينشتاين
as to how he imagined the forces of relativity,
لتخيله قوى النسبية
when he was struggling with trying to understand how it worked.
عندما كان يجاهد لمحاولة فهم طريقة عملها
But it happens in other activities.
ولكن الأمر يحدث في أنشطة أخرى
For instance, this is another student of mine,
فمثلا هذه طالبة أخرى من طلابي
Susan Jackson from Australia, who did work
سوزان جاكسون من أستراليا، قد عملت
with some of the leading athletes in the world.
مع بعض الرياضيين البارزين في العالم
And you see here in this description of an Olympic skater,
وترون هنا وصفًا لمتزلج أوليمبي
the same essential description of the phenomenology
وهو نفس الوصف تقريبًا لظواهر
of the inner state of the person.
الحالة الداخلية للإنسان
You don't think; it goes automatically,
ولا يعتقد أنها تحدث تلقائيًا
if you merge yourself with the music, and so forth.
إذا دمجت نفسك مع الموسيقى، وما إلى ذلك
It happens also, actually, in the most recent book I wrote,
وتحدث كذلك، في الواقع في أحدث كتبي
called "Good Business," where I interviewed some of the CEOs
المسمى "تجارة رابحة"، قابلت بعض المديرين التنفيذيين
who had been nominated by their peers as being both very successful
قد رشحهم نظراؤهم من حيث أنهم ناجحون جدًا
and very ethical, very socially responsible.
وكذلك على مستوى عالٍ من الأخلاق، أو المسؤولية الاجتماعية
You see that these people define success
ترون أن هؤلاء الأشخاص يعرّفون النجاح
as something that helps others and at the same time
بأنه أمر يساعد الآخرين وفي نفس الوقت
makes you feel happy as you are working at it.
يجعلك تشعر بالسعادة بأنك تقوم به
And like all of these successful and responsible CEOs say,
وكما يقول جميع هؤلاء المديريين التنفيذيين الناجحين والمسؤولين
you can't have just one of these things be successful
لا يمكنك النجاح إذا كان لديك واحد فقط من هذه الأمور
if you want a meaningful and successful job.
إذا أردت وظيفة ذات معنى ووظيفة ناجحة --
Anita Roddick is another one of these CEOs we interviewed.
أنيتا روديك هي مديرة أخرى من المديرين التنفيذيين الذي أجرينا معهم مقابلة
She is the founder of Body Shop,
وهي مؤسسة "بودي شوب"،
the natural cosmetics king.
وهي ملكة التجميل، التجميل الطبيعي
It's kind of a passion that comes
إنه نوع من العاطفة يأتي
from doing the best and having flow while you're working.
من فعل أفضل ما يمكن وأن تسير الأمور بتدفق عندما تعمل
This is an interesting little quote from Masaru Ibuka,
هذا اقتباس قصير مثير للاهتمام من "ماسارو إيبوكا"
who was at that time starting out Sony without any money,
الذي كان وقتها يبدأ في إنشاء شركة سوني دون أي مال
without a product -- they didn't have a product,
دون أي منتج -- لم يكن لديهم منتجًا
they didn't have anything, but they had an idea.
لم يكن لديهم أي شيء، ولكن كان عندهم فكرة
And the idea he had was to establish a place of work where engineers
وكانت فكرته هي إنشاء مكان عمل يستطيع فيه المهندسون
can feel the joy of technological innovation,
أن يشعروا بالسعادة من الابتكار التكنولوجي
be aware of their mission to society and work to their heart's content.
وأن يدركوا مهمتهم في المجتمع وأن يعملوا بما يرضي ضمائرهم
I couldn't improve on this as a good example
ولا أستطيع الإضافة على هذا الكلام، فهو مثال جيد
of how flow enters the workplace.
لكيفية دخول التدفق إلى مكان العمل
Now, when we do studies --
عندما نقوم بالدراسات
we have, with other colleagues around the world,
لقد أجرينا، مع زملائنا في أنحاء العالم
done over 8,000 interviews of people -- from Dominican monks,
أكثر من 8000 مقابلة مع الناس -- من الراهبين في الدومينيكان
to blind nuns, to Himalayan climbers, to Navajo shepherds --
إلى الراهبات المكفوفات، إلى متسلقي جبال الهمالايا، إلى رعاة أغنام من قبيلة الناباخو
who enjoy their work.
الذين يستمتعون بعملهم
And regardless of the culture,
وبغض النظر عن الثقافة
regardless of education or whatever, there are these seven conditions
وبغض النظر عن التعليم أو أي شيء، هناك سبعة شروط
that seem to be there when a person is in flow.
يبدو أنها تكون موجودة عندما يشعر شخص ما بالتدفق
There's this focus that, once it becomes intense,
هناك التركيز الذي ما أن يصبح قويًا
leads to a sense of ecstasy, a sense of clarity:
يؤدي إلى حالة من الاستغراق، حالة من الوضوح
you know exactly what you want to do from one moment to the other;
فتعرف بالضبط ما الذي تريد أن تقوم به من لحظة إلى أخرى
you get immediate feedback.
فأنت تحصل على تغذية فكرية فورية
You know that what you need to do
وتعرف أن ما عليك أن تفعله
is possible to do, even though difficult,
ممكن رغم أنه صعب
and sense of time disappears, you forget yourself,
ويختفي الإحساس بالزمن، وتنسى نفسك
you feel part of something larger.
وتشعر بأنك جزء من شيء أكبر
And once the conditions are present,
ما أن تتوافر هذه الشروط
what you are doing becomes worth doing for its own sake.
يصير ما تفعله مستحق الفعل في ذاته
In our studies, we represent the everyday life of people in this simple scheme.
في دراساتنا، نمثل الحياة العادية للناس في هذا المخطط البسيط
And we can measure this very precisely, actually,
ويمكننا أن نقيس ذلك بدقة كبيرة
because we give people electronic pagers that go off 10 times a day,
لأننا نعطي الناس أجهزة إلكترونية للرسائل، ترن 10 مرات في اليوم
and whenever they go off you say what you're doing, how you feel,
وكلما رنت، تسجل ما تفعله وكيف تشعر
where you are, what you're thinking about.
وأين أنت وما الذي تفكر فيه
And two things that we measure is the amount of challenge
ومن بين الأمور التي نقيسها
people experience at that moment and the amount of skill
حجم التحدي الذي يشعر به الناس في تلك اللحظة
that they feel they have at that moment.
وحجم المهارات التي يشعرون بأنهم يتمتعون بها في تلك اللحظة
So for each person we can establish an average,
وعلى ذلك نستطيع تحديد متوسط لكل شخص
which is the center of the diagram.
هو مركز الرسم
That would be your mean level of challenge and skill,
هذا هو مستواك المتوسط من التحدي والمهارة
which will be different from that of anybody else.
وهو مختلف عن مستوى أي شخص آخر
But you have a kind of a set point there, which would be in the middle.
ولكن لديك نقطة محددة هناك تكون في الوسط
If we know what that set point is,
إذا عرفنا ما هي هذه النقطة المحددة
we can predict fairly accurately when you will be in flow,
يمكننا أن نتوقع بدقة كبيرة أنك تشعر بتدفق
and it will be when your challenges are higher than average
ويكون ذلك عندما يعلو مستوى التحديات عن المتوسط
and skills are higher than average.
ويعلو مستوى المهارات عن المتوسط
And you may be doing things very differently from other people,
وقد تكون تفعل بعض الأمور بطريقة مختلفة عن الآخرين
but for everyone that flow channel, that area there,
ولكن لجميع الناس، قناة التدفق تلك، تلك المنطقة هناك
will be when you are doing what you really like to do --
تكون عندما تفعل شيئًا تحب أن تفعله --
play the piano, be with your best friend, perhaps work,
العزف على البيانو، مثلا، أن تكون برفقة أقرب أصدقائك، أو ربما تعمل
if work is what provides flow for you.
إذا كان العمل هو ما يجعلك تشعر بالتدفق
And then the other areas become less and less positive.
ثم تقل إيجابية المناطق الأخرى شيئًا فشيئا
Arousal is still good because you are over-challenged there.
الاستثارة جيدة أيضًا لأن التحدي يزيد في تلك المنطقة
Your skills are not quite as high as they should be,
ولا تكون مهاراتك على المستوى الذي يبنغي أن تكون عليه
but you can move into flow fairly easily
ولكنك تستطيع الوصول إلى التدفق بسهولة
by just developing a little more skill.
بأن تنمي مهاراتك بقدر قليل فقط
So, arousal is the area where most people learn from,
فالاستثارة إذًا هي المنطقة التي يتعلم منها معظم الناس
because that's where they're pushed beyond their comfort zone
لأنها المنطقة التي يدفع الناس فيها خارج منطقة راحتهم
and to enter that -- going back to flow --
ليدخلوا -- للعودة إلى التدفق --
then they develop higher skills.
وبذلك ينمون مهاراتهم
Control is also a good place to be,
والسيطرة كذلك منطقة جيدة
because there you feel comfortable, but not very excited.
لأنك هناك تشعر بالراحة، ولكنك لا تكون متحمسًا جدًا
It's not very challenging any more.
وينقطع هناك التحدي
And if you want to enter flow from control,
وإذا أردت أن تدخل حالة التدفق من خلال السيطرة
you have to increase the challenges.
عليك زيادة التحديات
So those two are ideal and complementary areas
فهاتان المنطقتان إذًا مثاليتان ومكملتان لبعضهما
from which flow is easy to go into.
ويمكن دخول حالة التدفق منهما بسهولة
The other combinations of challenge and skill
التركيبات الأخرى للتحدي والمهارة
become progressively less optimal.
تصبح أقل مثالية بشكل تدريجي
Relaxation is fine -- you still feel OK.
الاسترخاء لا بأس به، تشعر أنك بخير
Boredom begins to be very aversive
ويبدأ الضجر في أن يصبح منفرًا جدًا
and apathy becomes very negative:
وتصبح اللامبالاة سلبية جدًا
you don't feel that you're doing anything,
لا تشعر بأنك تفعل أي شيء
you don't use your skills, there's no challenge.
لا تستخدم مهاراتك وليس هناك تحدٍ
Unfortunately, a lot of people's experience is in apathy.
للأسف، كثير من شعور الناس يقع في منطقة اللامبالاة
The largest single contributor to that experience
وأكبر مساهم في هذا الشعور
is watching television; the next one is being in the bathroom, sitting.
هو مشاهدة التلفاز، يليه أن تكون في دورة المياه، جالسا
Even though sometimes watching television
وهنا، رغم أن مشاهدة التلفاز
about seven to eight percent of the time is in flow,
تسبب حالة من التدفق في سبعة إلى ثمانية في المائة من الحالات
but that's when you choose a program you really want to watch
ولكن ذلك يحدث عندما تختار برنامجًا ترغب فعلا في مشاهدته
and you get feedback from it.
وتحصل منه على ما يغذي فكرك
So the question we are trying to address -- and I'm way over time --
فالسؤال الذي نحاول الإجابة عليه -- قد تجاوزت وقتي بكثير --
is how to put more and more of everyday life in that flow channel.
هو كيف نضع مزيدًا من أحداث الحياة اليومية في قناة التدفق
And that is the kind of challenge that we're trying to understand.
وهذا هو التحدي الذي نحاول فهمه
And some of you obviously know how to do that spontaneously
وبالتأكيد بعضكم يعرف كيف يفعل ذلك بطريقة عفوية
without any advice, but unfortunately a lot of people don't.
دون أي نصيحة، ولكن للأسف هناك كثير من الناس لا يعرفون
And that's what our mandate is, in a way, to do.
وهذا هو هدف مهمتنا
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)